Guide to the J. Walter Thompson Company. Rena Bartos Papers, 1960-1998 and undated, bulk 1975-1991 RL.00664
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company. Rena Bartos papers
1960-2003 and undated bulk 1975-1991
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
J. Walter Thompson Company
RL.00664
28 Linear Feet
Rena Bartos worked as a marketing researcher, advertising executive, and consultant from 1960 to 1998. She directed research at the McCann Erickson advertising agency and held the position of Senior Vice President at the J. Walter Thompson Company before forming her own marketing consulting firm, The Rena Bartos Company. A pioneer in the field of marketing to women and an advocate for older adult consumers, Bartos was the recipient of numerous prestigous marketing and advertising industry awards, including the Matrix and Effie Awards. The Rena Bartos Papers consists of speeches and presentations, publications, research, and correspondence related to Bartos' career in the marketing research divisions of McCann Erickson and the J. Walter Thompson Company, spanning the years 1960-1998, with the bulk of the contents from 1975-1991. Other items in the collection include video and audio copies of speeches and presentations by Bartos, a brief history of the J. Walter Thompson Company, as well as drafts of articles and manuscripts.
11625 Items
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted.
Original audiovisual materials are closed to patron use. Use copies are available in the collection.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Rena Bartos Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1985-1997.
Biographical Note
Missing Title
1939 Graduated Cum Laude from Rutgers University
1964-1966 Director of Research, McCann Erickson
1966 Joined J. Walter Thompson as Head of Creative Research
1975 New York Chapter of Women in Communications Matrix Award YWCA Salute to Women in Business Award
1976 Advertising and Consumers: New Perspectives published
1977 The Founding Fathers of Advertising Research: A Tribute by the Advertising Research Foundation published in the Journal of Advertising Research Named Senior Vice President at J. Walter Thompson Company
1978 What Every Marketer Should Know About Women from the Harvard Business Review selected as a finalist for 1979 National Magazine Award
1979 Named Advertising Woman of the Year by Advertising Women of New York
1982 Named one of the 100 Most Important Women by Ladies Home Journal The Moving Target: What Every Marketer Should Know About Women published
1983 First female Chairperson of the Advertising Research Council
1985 Named Boston Professional Chapter of Women in Communications Matrix Award
1987 Inducted into the Market Research Hall of Fame Retired from J. Walter Thompson to form The Rena Bartos Company
1989 Named President of the Market Research Council Marketing to Women Around the World published in the United States. It would later be published in Germany and Great Britain
Collection Overview
The Rena Bartos Papers span the years 1960-1998, with the bulk of the material dating from 1975 to 1991. The collection documents Bartos' career through speeches and presentations, publications, correspondence, research files, slides, photographs and videotapes, while in positions at McCann Erickson, the J. Walter Thompson Company (JWT), and The Rena Bartos Company. Major topics include marketing to under-represented groups, the role of women in advertising, and Bartos' efforts to promote marketing towards women and over forty-nine adults. The collection is organized into five series and two indexes: Speeches and Presentations; Correspondence; Publications; Research Files; Audiovisual Materials; an Alphabetical List of Publications; and an Alphabetical List of Speech Titles
The Speeches and Presentations Series includes reading copies or scripts from speeches and presentations given by Bartos during her career. Dominant themes include the role of women in advertising, marketing to underrepresented groups such as women and people in Latin America and India, and the psychological aspects of advertising. In addition, the series includes the slides and graphics Bartos used in her speeches, as well as press clippings from her various speaking engagements.
The Correspondence Series includes business correspondence, mailings and solicitations from Bartos' career in marketing research, as well as correspondence with JWT executives, including Don Johnston and Thomas Sutton. The series also contains correspondence between Bartos and the various publishers of her written works.
The Publications Series includes copies of the articles written by Bartos for scholarly and trade publications such as The Harvard Business Review, the Journal of Advertising Research, Marketing Review, and Marketing and Research Today, either from the original periodical or in pre-print form.
The Research Series includes an extensive collection of newspaper and periodical clippings and other resources used by Bartos as supporting materials for her speaking engagements, articles, and books.
The Audiovisual Materials Series includes audio and visual recordings of promotional works for marketing campaigns, including The Moving Target. In addition, this series also includes tapes of speeches and interviews given by Bartos, some of which relate to the published article The Founding Fathers of Advertising Research.
Related Material
Related materials may be found in these collections in the JWT Archives: the Albert B. Stridsberg Papers, the Thomas Sutton Papers, the Don Johnston Papers, and the Joseph O'Donnell Papers.
Alphabetical List of Publications
Ads That Irritate May Erode Trust in Advertised Brands, 1981, Box 13
Beyond Derived Status, 1986 Box 14
Beyond the Cookie Cutters, 1981 Box 13
Challenging Our Assumptions, 1986 Box 14
Cinq tendences qui détermineront le marketing et la publicité dans les années 90, 1989 Box 14
Consumer View of Advertising--1974, 1975 Box 13
Exploring Mysterious Markets, 1979 Box 13
Founding Fathers of Advertising Research (with Arthur S. Pearson), 1977 Box 13
Founding Fathers of Advertising Research, 1986 Box 14
Future of the Advertising Agency Research Function, 1974 Box 13
How to Advertise to Women, 1995 Box 14
Insight on Selling the Working Woman, 1976 Box 13
International Advertising: Consumers, the Moving Target, 1984, Box 13
International Demographic Data? Incomparable! 1989 Box 14
Keeping Up With Changing Life Cycles, 1978 Box 13
Marketing Research: The Moving Target, 1976 Box 13
Moving Target, circa 1974 Box 13
Moving Target: Customer for Life Insurance, 1976 Box 13
Moving Target: The American Consumer 1970-1990, circa 1978, Box 13
Moving Target: The Impact of Women's Employment on Consumer Behavior, 1977 Box 13
New Woman, 1985 Box 14
Over 49: The Invisible Consumer Market, 1980, 1983 Box 13
Over 49: The Invisible Consumer Market, 1993 Box 14
Qualitative Research: What It Is and Where It Came From, 1985-1986 Box 14
Quiet Revolution, 1989 Box 14
Report of a Study Conducted on the Image of Women in Advertising, undated Box 13
Research, Creativity, and Tunnel Vision, undated Box 14
Target is Moving, 1975 Box 13
Target is Moving: The Changing Bank Customer, 1978 Box 13
Target: Latin America--The Changing Consumer Marketplace, undated Box 13
What About the Consumer Who Brushes His Teeth With Shampoo? 1984, Box 13
What Every Marketer Should Know About Women, 1978, 1983 Box 13
What Women Like, and Don't Like, In Ads, 1982 Box 13
Why Do You Work? 1979 Box 13
Women and Advertising, 1983 Box 13
Women and Travel, 1982 Box 13
Women As a Moving Target: Will It Continue? undated Box 14
Women: A Missed Mega Market? 1989 Box 14
Women's Forum, Inc.: The First 15 Years, 1990 Box 14
Alphabetical List of Speech Titles
Acceptance Speech, Market Research Council, 1989 Box 4
Advertisers and Consumers--New Perspectives, 1977 Box 1
Advertising and Credibility, 1984 Box 2
Advertising and Credibility, 1986 Box 3
Advertising and the Economy, 1975 Box 1
Advertising Research... What Should Be Measured? 1981 Box 1
Advertising: What...Why... How..., 1986 Box 3
Attitude of Mothers and Young Children Toward Toy Purchases and Toy TV Commercials, 1962 Box 1
Beyond the Cookie Cutter, 1984 Box 3
Beyond the Cookie Cutter, II, 1988 Box 4
Beyond the Rocking Chair, 1981 Box 1
Beyond the Rocking Chair, 1988 Box 4
Challenge of Change, 1986, 1988 Box 4
Challenging Our Assumption, 1986 Box 3
Challenging Our Assumptions About the Marketplace, 1990, 1992, Box 5
Changes and Challenges, 1985, 1986 Box 3
Changing Consumer Marketplace: Five Trends That Will Redefine Marketing and Advertising, 1987, 1988 Box 4
Consumer Behavior During Inflationary Times: Panel Discussion, 1981 Box 1
Consumer Profile of the 1980s, 1980 Box 1
Consumer Trends in the United States, 1989 Box 4
Customer for Life Insurance: A Moving Target, 1976 Box 1
Demographic and Social Trends in North America, 1990 Box 4
Demographics of Older Shoppers, 1982 Box 2
Do We Really Have to Make Them Mad to Sell Them? 1980 Box 1
Does Social Research Have Real Value in Marketing Decsions? 1982, Box 2
Effect of Changing Population Demographics on the Data Collection Profession, 1979 Box 1
Excellence in Advertising: Today and Tomorrow, 1984 Box 3
Exploration of Food Habits and Attitudes of Far Eastern Students, 1972 Box 1
Facts of Life, 1982, 1984 Box 2
Facts of Life: The Changing Consumer Marketplace, 1985 Box 3
Facts of Life: The Changing Consumer Marketplace, 1986, 1987, Box 4
Facts of Life: The Changing Supermarket Shopper, 1985 Box 3
Facts of Life: The Changing Supermarket Shopper, 1986 Box 4
Home Economics, 1977 Box 1
Honoring Women's Impact on the Economy: Yesterday and Today, 1998 Box 5
International Moving Target: The Changing Role of Women Around the World, 1987 Box 4
Keeping Pace with the Changing Women's Market Around the World, 1990 Box 4
Marketing Financial Services to Changing Customers, 1985 Box 3
Marketing the ERA, undated Box 5
Marketing to the Pacific Rim, 1985 Box 3
Marketing to Women Around the World, 1988-1990 Box 4
Marketing to Women in Canada and the United States, 1990 Box 4
Marketing Yourself, 1989 Box 4
Matrix Award Acceptance Speech, 1986 Box 3
Meeting the Cosmetic Needs of Tomorrow's Consumers: Changing Demographics and Changing Attitudes, 1983 Box 2
Moving Target, 1978-1980 Box 1
Moving Target, 1982-1983 Box 2
Moving Target: A New Look at the Consumer Marketplace, 1983, Box 2
Moving Target: A New Look at the Consumer Marketplace, 1984-1985, Box 3
Moving Target: Consumer Trends in the 1980s, 1983-1984 Box 2
Moving Target: The Changing Customer for Financial Services, 1985 Box 3
Moving Target: The Changing Women's Market, 1978 Box 1
Moving Target: The Changing Women's Market, 1982 Box 2
Moving Target: The Influence of Women's Employment on Consumer Behavior, 1977 Box 1
Moving Target: The Women's Car Market, 1987 Box 4
Moving Target: What Every Marketer Should Know About Women, 1989, Box 4
Moving Target--Changing Demographics--Changing Attitudes, 1983-1984 Box 2
Opportunites, 1982 Box 2
Opportunities and How to Capitalize on Them, 1976 Box 1
Over 49, 1984 Box 3
Over 49: The Invisible Consumer Market, 1986 Box 3
Overview: Setting the Context, 1989 Box 4
Perspectives on Women in Their Consuming Roles: The Moving Target, 1990 Box 4
Presentation of Market Research Hall of Fame to Henry Brenner, 1992 Box 5
Qualitative Research: What It Is and Where It Came From, 1985, Box 3
Reaching The Moving Target, 1992 Box 5
Reaching the Young Customer: A Strategy for Success in the Nineties, 1989 Box 4
Remarks at Memorial Service to Honor Dr. Ernest Dichter, 1992, Box 5
Research Creativity and Tunnel Vision, 1973 Box 1
Savings Market, undated Box 5
Seminar on Marketing to Women Around the World, 1989 Box 4
Social Change and the Travel Marketer, 1976 Box 1
Social Change Means New Marketing Opportunities, 1981 Box 1
Social Trends of the 80s, 1980 Box 1
Solving the Communications Puzzle, 1984 Box 2
Some Observations on Gender in Advertising, 1990 Box 4
Systems Approach to Research, 1964 Box 1
Target is Moving--The Changing Bank Customer, 1978 Box 1
Targeting the Top, 1984 Box 2
Trends in American Advertising, 1972 Box 1
Tribute to Ruth Whitney, 1993 Box 5
Use of Qualitative Evaluation: Problems, Pitfalls, and Potentials, 1983 Box 2
Use of the 1976 Survey of Income and Education, 1978 Box 1
Using Census Data, 1979 Box 1
Welcome from the Chairwoman, 1977 Box 1
Who Pipes, Who Pays, and Who Calls the Tune--The Agency Viewpoint, 1973 Box 1
Who Pipes, Who Pays, Who Calls the Tune? 1974 Box 1
Why a Full Service Industry? 1973 Box 1
Woman's Place (And Yours): A Changing Market, 1973 Box 1
Women as a Moving Target, 1978 Box 1
Women's Car Market: A Moving Target, 1990 Box 4
Working Woman Audience: The Moving Target, 1976 Box 1
Working Women: The Invisible Consumer Travel Market, 1973, Box 1
Speeches; Audiocassettes; Clippings (information artifacts); Photographs; Women in advertising; Advertising; Rena Bartos Company; Videocassettes; Minorities in advertising; Women consumers -- United States; Advertising executives; Aged consumers -- United States; Advertising -- Awards; Advertising -- Psychological aspects; Marketing -- Latin America; Slides (photographs); Market research; Marketing; Marketing -- India; Bartos, Rena; Bartos, Rena. Moving target; J. Walter Thompson Company; Johnston, Don; John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History; Sutton, Thomas (Thomas Francis); McCann-Erickson Worldwide
- Speech and Presentation Series, 1960-1998 and undated, 11 boxes
  Scope and Contents note
  Consists of copies of speeches and some working scripts (where available) for presentations and addresses delivered by Bartos between 1962 and 1998. In addition, the series also includes speeches from various JWT executives, slides and graphics used by Bartos during her presentations, and clippings and ephemera from her speaking engagements and career milestones. Series is organized into two subseries: Speeches and Supporting Materials.
  - Speeches Subseries, 1960-1998 and undated
    Includes speeches and presentations given by Bartos during her career. A chronological list of speeches is located in Box 5. The speeches are arranged chronologically to preserve their original order; an alphabetical listing of speech titles appears at the end of the finding aid.
    - Chronological file of speeches
      - 1962-1982, 34 folders (Box 1)
      - 1982-1984, 32 folders (Box 2)
      - 1984-1986, 32 folders (Box 3)
      - 1986-1990, 18 folders (Box 4)
      - 1990-1998 and undated, 22 folders (Box 5)
    - Chronological list of speeches (printed list in folder), 1962-1998 and undated (Box 5)
    - J. Walter Thompson Company executive speeches, 1960-1980s and undated (Box 5)
  - Supporting Materials Subseries, 1966-1995 and undated
    Includes graphics, slides, and press files from Bartos' speaking engagements. Some of the files relate to various projects and presentations that Bartos produced, but actual dates cannot be determined for many items.
    - Graphics, 1971-1990 and undated (Box 5)
      Primarily statistical charts and drafts of data presentations. Arranged alphabetically.
      - Adult trends, 1985-1987 (Box 5)
      - All titles, 1986 (Box 5)
      - Baby boomers, 1985-1987 (Box 5)
      - Canada, 1984-1987 (Box 5)
      - Challenging our assumptions, undated (Box 5)
      - Colorless slides, 1985 (Box 5)
      - Consumer opportunities, 1986 (Box 5)
      - Credibility, circa 1985 (Box 5)
      - Detroit auto dealers, 1987-1990 (Box 5)
      - Facts of life, 1990 (Box 5)
      - International moving target, 1987 (Box 5)
      - Japan, 1980-1986 (Box 5)
      - Latin America, 1990, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Marketing to women around the world, 1988 (Box 5)
      - Media, 1985-1986, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Moving target, 1990 (Box 5)
      - MRB (Market Research Britain)-Great Britain, 1971-1986 (Box 5)
      - New demographics, undated (Box 6)
      - Over 49 market, 1990 (Box 6)
      - Women, 1985-1988, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Miscellaneous
        - General, 1987-1990 (Box 6)
        - International, 1987-1991, 2 folders (Box 6)
        - Verbals/Visuals, undated (Box 6)
    - Press files, 1966-1995 and undated
      Newspaper and periodical clippings about Bartos' career. Arranged alphabetically.
      - Book reviews for Marketing to Women Around the World, 1988-1991, 4 folders (Box 6)
      - Brazil, 1980, 1989, 2 folders (Box 6)
      - Effie Awards, 1976-1995 (Box 6)
      - Press files, 1966-1973, 7 folders (Box 6)
      - Press files, 1974-1987, 17 folders (Box 7)
      - Press files, 1988-1995 and undated, 7 folders (Box 8)
    - Slides, undated
      Slides for Bartos' speaking engagements. Dates cannot be accurately determined. Arranged alphabetically.
      - ARF (Advertising Research Foundation) (Box 8)
      - Baby boomers
        - Media (Box 8)
        - Products (Box 8)
        - Extras (Box 8)
      - Changing face of fashion (Box 8)
      - Credibility (Box 8)
      - Detroit (Box 8)
      - ERA (Equal Rights Ammendment), 2 folders (Box 8)
      - box 9 (Box 9)
      - Facts of life, 3 folders (Box 9)
      - Financial (Box 9)
      - JWT Board Meeting, 5, November 1982 (Box 9)
      - Marketing to women around the world, 2 folders (Box 9)
      - Media (Box 9)
      - Miscomprehension I (Box 9)
      - Miscomprehension II (Box 9)
      - Over forty-nine, 2 folders
        - Advertising imagery (Box 9)
        - Extras, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Pacific Rim (Box 10)
      - Physical fitness (Box 10)
      - Research and development presentation (Box 10)
      - Scottsdale (Box 10)
      - Weight concern (Box 10)
      - Women, 2 folders (Box 10)
      - Women and the car market (Box 10)
      - Miscellaneous, 2 folders
        - Graphs (Box 10)
        - Updates (Box 10)
        - Verbals, 3 folders (Box 11)
        - Visuals, 7 folders (Box 11)
- Correspondence Series, 1971-1995 and undated, 3 boxes
  Includes correspondence and memoranda that document Bartos' involvement in a range of market research activities, including JWT's Special Markets project, marketing to women and minorities, and Bartos' own Moving Target project. Also included is correspondence that details the career of Joseph O'Donnell. The series is organized into two subseries: J. Walter Thompson Company Subseries and The Rena Bartos Company Subseries and chronologically therein.
  - J. Walter Thompson Company Subseries, 1971-1995 and undated
    Arranged chronologically.
    - 1971-1977, 24 folders (Box 11)
    - 1978-1987, 14 folders (Box 12)
      Folders 1985-1987 contain information on JWT executive Joseph O'Donnell.
    - 1981-1995 and undated, Correspondence with Tom Sutton (Box 12)
      Sutton (1923-1994) was Executive Vice President of JWT until his retirement in 1983.
  - The Rena Bartos Company Subseries, 1988-1995 and undated
    - 1988-1991, 6 folders (Box 12)
    - 1992-1995 and undated, 3 folders (Box 13)
- Publications Series, 1966-1995 and undated, 2 boxes
  Consists of copies of newspaper and periodical articles written by Bartos during her career and various internal reports Bartos created for the J. Walter Thompson Company, including What Every Marketer Should Know About Women for The Harvard Business Review and Qualitative Research: What Is It and Where Did It Come From? for The Journal of Advertising Research. In addition, the series contains articles from various JWT Company publications documenting the history of the company, including the attempted takeover of the company by Joseph O'Donnell in 1986, and transcripts of two interviews with Bartos. The series is organized into two subseries: Personal Publications and J. Walter Thompson Company History.
  - Personal Publications Subseries, 1967-1995 and undated
    Includes articles, reports and drafts written by Bartos. Arranged alphabetically. An alphabetical index of Bartos' publications appears at the end of the finding aid.
    - Drafts, undated (Box 13)
    - Interview transcripts, undated, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - J. Walter Thompson Company reports, 1967-1986, 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Publications, 1973-1995 and undated
      - 1973-1984, 11 folders (Box 13)
      - 1985-1995 and undated, 8 folders (Box 14)
  - J. Walter Thompson Company History Subseries, circa 1966-1987 and undated
    Arranged alphabetically.
    - Annual reports, 1970-1979 (Box 14)
    - Articles relating to company history, 1966-1987 (Box 14)
      Includes articles on the attempted takeover of the J. Walter Thompson Company by Joseph O'Donnell in 1986.
    - Newsletters, 1966-1986, 3 folders (Box 14)
    - Photographs, undated, 2 folders (Box 14)
- Research Series, circa 1960-1996 and undated, 14 boxes
  Consists of newspaper clippings, periodical articles, interview transcripts, and papers published by other marketing researchers which were used by Bartos during her career. Includes page proofs and research for books and articles, including The Moving Target, Marketing to Women Around the World, Over 49: The Invisible Consumer Market and What Every Marketer Should Know About Women from The Harvard Business Review. Organized into two subseries: Clippings and Documents and Published Materials.
  - Clippings and Documents Subseries, circa 1960-1995 and undated
    Newspaper clippings, magazine articles, typed reports, trade brochures and drafts of reports collected to oprovide background and context for Bartos' writings. Arranged alphabetically.
    - AAAA (American Association of Advertising Agencies) advertising careers, 1960 and undated (Box 15)
    - Advertising and women, 1978-1995 and undated, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - Aging, 1978-1980 and undated (Box 15)
    - American consumers, 1977-1982 (Box 15)
    - Attitudes towards advertisers, undated (Box 15)
    - Baby boomers, 1975-1990 and undated
      - General, 1975-1990 (Box 15)
      - Backups, 1975-1990 (Box 15)
      - Illustrations, 1975-1989 and undated (Box 15)
    - Barbara Bryant, 1983 and undated, 2 folders (Box 15)
      Includes articles written by marketer Barbara Bryant, of the Heritage Society.
    - Changes in womens lives, 1979-1981
      - General, 1979-1980, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Phenomenon of women's work, 1979-1981 (Box 15)
      - Types of women's work, 1979-1981, 4 folders (Box 16)
      - Why women work, 1979-1981 (Box 16)
      - Will it continue, 1980-1981 (Box 16)
    - Children, 1977-1980 (Box 16)
    - Cohabitation and other alternatives to marriage, 1977-1980 (Box 16)
    - Corporate women, 1983-1988 and undated, 2 folders (Box 16)
    - Divorce, 1977-1980 (Box 16)
    - Doyle Dane study, 1979 (Box 16)
    - ERA (Equal Rights Ammendment), 1980-1981 and undated, 3 folders (Box 16)
    - Ethnic markets, 1983-1988 and undated (Box 17)
    - Family, 1977-1990 and undated
      - General, 1977-1980 (Box 17)
      - American family, 1985-1990 (Box 17)
      - Family and work, 1988-1990, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Food habits of Far Eastern children, undated (Box 17)
    - Glass ceiling, circa 1985-1993, 2 folders (Box 17)
    - Hispanic marketing, 1989 and undated (Box 17)
    - Ideal lifestyle questions, 1983 (Box 17)
    - Impact of working women, 1986-1989 and undated (Box 17)
    - Marriage, 1977-1980 and undated (Box 17)
    - Men, 1987-1992 and undated (Box 17)
    - Miscomprehension, 1980-1987 and undated, 2 folders (Box 18)
    - Moving Target, 1976-1977
      - Book proposal, undated (Box 18)